# **Muhammad Ahmar Jamal**

Dorm 77, Bilkent University Çankaya, Ankara

(+90) 5527334697 ahmarjamal30@gmail.com

### PERSONAL PROFILE

An enthusiastic B.Sc. Electrical and Electronics student at Bilkent university with strong academic and co-curricular achievements. Possess multiple internship experiences and strong leadership skills. As an undergraduate student, keen to learn more about the practical applications of science and gain work experience in the electrical industry.

### **EDUCATION**

## Bilkent University | Ankara, Turkey

Aug 2021 - present

B.Sc. ELECTRICAL AND ELECTRONICS ENGINEERING

CGPA 3.52

**Relevant courses** (**Taken**): Analog Electronics, Engineering Mathematics I, Introduction to Digital Circuit Design, Introduction to Programming in Python, Calculus I & II, General Physics I & II

Relevant courses this semester: Circuit Theory, Microprocessors, Engineering Mathematics II

#### Lahore Grammar School | Lahore, Pakistan

Jun 2019 - Jun 2021

GCE Advanced Level: (3A\*s)

Subjects: Mathematics (A\*), Physics (A\*), Chemistry (A\*)

### Beaconhouse School System | Lahore, Pakistan

Jun 2016 - Jun 2019

GCE Ordinary Level: (9A\*s, 1A)

*Subjects*: Mathematics (A\*), Physics (A\*), Chemistry (A\*), Biology (A\*), Environmental management (A\*), Global Perspectives (A\*), Islamiat (A\*), Pakistan Studies (A\*), Urdu (A\*), English (A)

## WORK EXPERIENCE

## Pakistan Railways

Jun 2022 – Aug 2022

Trainee Electrical Engineer at Mughalpura Workshop

- Acquired knowledge of electrical and mechanical workshops' working of the largest governmental sector of Pakistan under the guidance of an experienced Electrical Foreman.
- At the end of program, successfully passed a practical test, demonstrating proficiency in identifying and repairing issues in the electrical circuits of locomotives.

## **Rural Community Development Program**

Jun 2018 – Jun 2020

Intern as Welfare Worker in Poverty Alleviation Program

- Attended group meetings and helped in developing presentations for it, conducted different surveys and recorded the results.
- Created and maintained a list of farmers in district 'Sheikhupura'.
- Visited Futtowala, Mehta Suja, Chak 44 and other villages with a team, persuaded **100+ farmers** to use solar energy to power their tube wells.

## Amin Medical Complex, Khanewal.

*Mar* 2020 – *Apr* 2020

Volunteer

- Raised awareness regarding SOPs issued by the Government of Pakistan during the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Ensured SOPs were implemented by the patients, their families and in different departments of the hospital including eyes, dental and physiotherapy.

#### **Lahore Literary Festival**

Jan 2020 - Jan 2020

Head of all volunteers

- Arranged group meetings on regular intervals, assigned duties to others volunteers and organized food for them.
- Managed the crowd in rush hours with the security team.
- Conveyed the timings of talks to several celebrities and escorted them from the general lounge to the talk areas.
- Divided volunteers into different departments to ensure the event was a success.

### **ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING PROJECTS**

**TRC- 11** (**Transmitter-Receiver**): Built a radio with High-Frequency transmitter-receiver operating in the 11-meter amateur band at 27Mhz. Discrete passive components and active integrated circuits were used to implement the analog signal processing required in the transceiver.

**Automated Boom Barrier**: The Basys3 board, Arduino Mega 2560, Ultrasonic sensor HC-SR04, and RC servo motor SG90, RFID reader RDM6300 and 125 kHz cards were used to make a real-world automated gated barrier that permits only authorized people to pass. VHDL was used as the major programming language, and C++ (Arduino) was used for the operation of RFID scanner.

#### **HONORS & ACHIEVMENTS**

#### STEM:

- High- Honor International Student with Full Merit Scholarship at Bilkent University, currently ranked 20<sup>th</sup> out of 150 students in the cohort of 2021.
- Full Merit Scholarship in all years of O-Levels and A-Levels.
- SAT:  $1490 \text{ (Maths} = 800, English} = 690).$
- World Education Games (organized by UNICEF and Microsoft): World Maths Day (1<sup>st</sup> in Pakistan and 5<sup>th</sup> in World), World Science Day (1<sup>st</sup> in Pakistan and 5<sup>th</sup> in World), World Literacy Day (1<sup>st</sup> in Pakistan and 2<sup>nd</sup> in World).
- 11<sup>th</sup> International Kangroo Science Contest 2018 (4<sup>th</sup> in Pakistan), Part of Beaconhouse International Student Convention Bangkok, Runner up of STEM Competition, Pakistan 2017.

#### **DEBATES:**

President Urdu Debates Society 2019-2020 (LGS), President Urdu Debating Club 2017-2018 (Beaconhouse), Head
of Publications at CSBC-MUN 2017, Special Award winner of SUPARCO Debates Competition 2017, Winner of
Debates Competition held during Faiz International Festival 2017 and OPERA 2018.

#### THEATRE

• Vice President Dramatic Club 2017 (BSS), had lead roles in many annual school plays, 1st position in Poetry Recitation Competition 2017, 2018 and 2019.

## **TABLE TENNIS:**

Head of Table tennis at JT Fest 2019 and at CSBC Sports Enthusia 2018, Winner of Bilkent United Spring
tournament and Fall tournament, Runner up of XVII. ANGORA cup, Winner of singles and doubles at SICAS
Sports Fest 2020, JT Fest 2019, Para-knight Olympics 2019, UCL A-Level Sports Fest 2019, Misaal 5.0, CSBC
Sports Enthusia 2018, Intra Region Table tennis Tournament 2018, JT Sports Fest 2017, JT Sports Fest 2016.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- PCB Design
- Python
- VHDL
- Assembly
- C
- LTspice
- MATLAB
- Oscilloscopes
- Microsoft office: Proficient in Word, Excel and PowerPoint.
- CorelDraw

#### ADITTIONAL SKILLS

• Languages: Urdu (*Native*), English (*Fluent*), Hindi (*Fluent*), Punjabi (*Fluent*) and Turkish (*Moderate*).